[Music]
Hi and welcome to this launch edition.
My name is Peter and with me in studio
today I have Vasil.
>> Thanks Peter.
>> The page scripting tool widely used uh
by consultants and customer stakeholders
empowers you to define and run user
acceptance tests directly in the
business central web client. Based on
user feedback, this release adds
improvements to the experience of
recording and editing scripts that makes
user accessment testing easier and more
efficient. So, keep watching this
session to see the new enhancements.
Basil and I will introduce some
enhancements to the page scripting tool
that we launched in preview some
releases ago.
Page scripting allows customers and
consultants to record and replay user
actions directly in the web client. For
example, as part of user acceptance
test, thereby offloading developers and
empowering customers and consultants to
create tests in a more agile, quicker,
and more cost effective way.
I did a thorough walkthrough of this new
exciting tool at launch. So if this is
new to you, I highly recommend watching
uh that session either before you
continue with this uh or after. And
we'll add the links in the description
as well. Let's see what we added in this
release.
To begin with, we have focused on
enhancing the experience of recording
acceptance tests by allowing steps
modification.
During the process of recording scripts,
we can make mistakes or sometimes forget
to perform certain actions.
Until now, the only way to get out of
this situation was either to delete the
last step until you reach the point of
the error, but then you basically lost
the all of those deleted steps. You
could re-record uh the test from the
beginning, or you could open the YAML
file, the script YAML file, and manually
remove or rearrange the steps.
But now you can define the insertion
point for steps. You can rearrange the
sequence of steps by using drag and drop
to set them in the correct order. And
you can delete not only the last step
but any step in the recording. To show
you this in the product I have with me
Vasil.
Thanks Peter.
So uh let's see how this looks in the
product.
So I have my customer card open and I
have loaded a script for customer
creation flow that I've created
previously. So now I want to extend it
and add additional steps. Whereas
previously one could have recreated the
script from scratch or performed manual
stitching in YAML. In version 27, you
can start recording from the page
scripting pane
and you can add an insert point where
you want to continue recording from by
pressing right click on the uh steps
pane and then you have the option record
from here. Now we see a red blinking
light which signals the corourser and
this is the place where the next step is
going to be inserted. So I can go ahead
and continue recording and I can add
values and you can see that the step is
added at the correct position and I'm
done with editing but I can see now that
I've made mistake where uh I can see
that the multiple multiple steps are
being added because I have been editing
my script. So in this version you can
also remove steps which are out of
sequence. So if I press delete, this is
removed from the recording and I can fix
the state that I've uh created. Um but
it comes with a warning. Remember that
changing steps out of order uh can come
with a price if you remove a step that
is detrimental for the subsequent uh
steps in the recording. Uh you can of
course close this error message which
could be again visible to remind you at
the page um title. Uh however, if you
like to make certain changes that should
follow a different se sequence than the
one that you have um already created,
you can use drag and drop to uh reorder
the sequence of steps.
Very nice, Vasil. Um I use this myself
and this will certainly uh help improve
the experience of creating scripts. So
just to quickly summarize uh what V was
showed, you can now set the recording
point. So you can insert uh steps uh
somewhere in the middle of a an existing
script. Um you can also rearrange the
sequence by using a drag and drop and
you can also delete steps in the middle
of a script. So you don't have to start
deleting uh from the end.
So then we have uh parameters and
suites. Uh parameters allow passing
values to a script. uh and suites allow
combining multiple uh scripts. Um that
could be for instance to to uh to set up
data first and until now both required
editing directly in the script YAML file
but now you can actually do it directly
in the client making it a lot easier to
use these features.
Thanks Peter. So as parameters is not a
new concept for page scripting, what is
new for version 27 is that you can edit,
view and create parameters through the
UI. So let's take the previous scripts
from the customer creation flow as an
example where we have a script where we
type a very specific values. So in order
for us to create modular scripts that
could be further reused for other
scenarios, it's smart to parameterize
the script. So starting with version 27,
if you see the properties of the script
recording, you can see the parameters
section where you can create, edit, and
view all your parameters from the
current recordings that you've created
or add new and then reuse them. Now
let's talk about creating test suits.
While suits are also not new, this could
have been previously done by manually
modifying the ML files. From version 27,
you can use Business Central and create
suits right from the UI. So I have a
script which is just a simple customer
creation uh flow and I want to reuse the
previously created script for customer
creation that I can always use new data
to create my um assertions.
I can rightclick on the steps pane and
then I can add a new step which is
called include a script. From here I can
select which script I want to include in
my current recording and uh same as
previously it would be added to my
current recording. So uh we talked about
parameters and we created a script that
requires a parameter. When you include a
script that requires parameters, the
properties pane would open and you will
be prompted to enter values for these
required parameters. So you can either
pass a hard-coded values or you can
propagate parameters from your root
level uh script or your test suit
further to the included scripts. So you
can do that by accessing the parameters
um uh property and then you can pass
your current parameter name.
So once I'm done and I want to start the
recording, you're prompted to add value
to the parameters that you have set as
required.
Two important things to be aware when
including a script is that before you
can include a script, your current
recording must be persisted to the disk
because all included scripts are
relative to the path of your current
script. And number two, if the included
script is in a different directory
relative to the script which you have
currently um where you currently are,
you have to manually specify the path
relative to your current script as from
the browser side we don't have access to
your file system.
Thanks facil. So um again to summarize h
you can define parameters now directly
in the UI along uh with setting in a
default value. So it'll be asked if uh
if you didn't set a default value on
executing the script. Uh and also you
can create these suites uh directly
inside of the client. Right? So for
instance to set up data prior to your
main uh script. Um as we still talked
about uh the insertter scripts they
can't be edited in the suite and you
have to remember things like uh using a
relative path. Yeah, one of the common
questions we had on suites was around
passing parameters and you saw how easy
it was to either set the parameters for
that exact um script in the suite or
actually passing parameters across uh
the um uh the suite from the sort of
main root uh script the sweet script. So
um the third sort of area topic here is
that sometimes we want our script to
iterate over entries in a list. Uh so
Vasil, have we done anything new that
can help with that?
>> Yes, we do. So uh let's start a
recording and imagine a scenario where
we want to uh create a script where we
want to move inventory. So while you can
of course go one by one and filter
specific rows where you want to change
with version 27 you can right click in
any repeater and then uh you have the
for each row option. What this would do
is would create a new scope where you
going to iterate over every single item
of this list. And now for each of the
items I can open them and then
set the shelf number to the desired
value. For example, number two and I can
close this. So once I'm done with my
scope, I can repeat this scenario and
this would iterate for every item in the
list until we are done. And this is
enough to set up your flow.
>> Great, Brazil. So again when you have
lists you can now add a for each so that
you can loop uh or have the script loop
over uh each of the entries there and
perform additional steps um on the
items. So something a little bit uh
related to that is conditional uh
branching on an expression. So I mean
what if what if you want to um for
instance uh looping over something but
not have every one of the entries being
processed but just under certain uh
conditions. Uh what do we have there?
>> Yes. So so far what you could do is that
you could use the validate step to
assess certain conditions.
With version 27, you can add an
additional step which is expression is
true. Meaning that you can dynamically
evaluate a certain expression and it's
only then within that scope that these
steps are going to execute. If for
example there are only certain users
that could perform certain steps due to
permissions, you could use this um uh
step to define a conditional execution
based on the current user. for example.
So I can use if this user ID that's
executing the scripts is administrator
and only in this case I want to perform
setting the shelf number. In this case
you can have conditional execution on
custom conditions.
>> Very nice facil. So again to summarize
you can now insert conditional steps
evaluated by a custom expression. A year
ago, we added support for replaying
scripts in pipelines.
You can watch the recording. I provided
a link. You can find a link uh below in
descriptions.
This relies on replaying in a browser.
The advantage is the ability to create a
video of the run, but it also comes at a
performance penalty.
That's why we are now adding the option
to run scripts headless on the server
side. This is still in preview and it is
uh on premise only or in containers
only.
Thanks Peter. I hope that by now you're
familiar with BC Replay but in order to
use server replay you of course still
need to uh install the npm package by
adding npm install at Microsoft BC
Replay. What's new in this release is
one switch that changes where the
scripts are being executed.
So I have already installed my u bc
replay in this directory. So I can just
execute the replay command. I can pass
my test files where they are.
Then I need to provide the start address
and just use server replay.
The difference in here is instead of
having the browser orchestrating the
script execution, we rely on server side
for these to execute.
And once the execution is done, the only
difference between server and browser
replay is that for server replay, we
don't have video recordings and there is
nothing to record from.
So as Vil showed you, you can now run
scripts headlessly in pipelines. You
simply add the use server replay
parameter when you're using BC replay.
So let's provide a summary of this
session.
In uh this release, we have focused on
improving uh the usability when you're
using page scripting. Uh, the page
scripting feature is still in preview,
but it is production quality and there
should be no reason for you to not use
it.
As always, uh, please give us feedback
on ak.ms/bc
ideas or on viva engage on the page
scripting tool.
uh and I can say we also know uh already
there's many of you who would like to
use this tool for for instance to create
documentation or training material
including screenshots and we acknowledge
the value for this but it's currently
not in our immediate backlog.
So as always uh there's a lot of
different uh business center resources
that you can use. I mentioned uh BC
ideas but uh we have a you know yama
groups we have a LinkedIn profile uh we
have a YouTube channel and in fact
here's a slide promoting our LinkedIn um
uh account and also our videos on
YouTube where you can see more sessions
not just from this release but also some
of the past releases. Thank you for
watching.